

Vitoria-Gasteiz (Alava) - Spain

(0034)660053476



Personal Website: https://davidsantamaria.me/

https://www.linkedin.com/in/davidsantamaria/ Linkedin Profile:

RESUME OBJECTIVE

Senior Engineering Manager - Senior Software Engineer

Senior Engineering Manager with 10+ years of experience managing individuals who enjoy helping out teams and individuals succeed. Supporting and growing the individuals that work surrounding me. I value and encourage teamwork, a continuous improvement mindset, delivering value to customers, commitment, empowerment, and humility.

I have comprehensive experience leading and working with engineering teams in the architecture, specification, and implementation of complex, highly scalable, and performant systems.

I am a Software engineer interested in software analysis, architecture, and development. The Web has been my focus. I love to build things with quality, from conception to deployment. I take the software that I write very seriously while having an extreme passion for being the best I can be at doing what I love to do.

EXPERIENCE



Toptal, Remote, Spain — Sr Engineering Manager

JUN 2021 - PRESENT

Tech Stack: React, Next, Ruby, RoR, Google Cloud Platform, K8s.

Role: Senior Engineering Manager at Toptal. Working on TopAcademy vertical. TopAcademy aims to be the most innovative and successful initiative in Toptal to solve the candidate sourcing.

- Lead a team of 10 software engineers, the first team in TopAcademy.
- Partner with the leadership to **create the TopAcademy initiative**.

Shipped:

- Definition of the initiative and lead the creation of the first team.
- Creation of the Frontend Path and collaboration for the Backend path.



Cloudbeds, Remote, Spain — Sr Engineering Manager

OCT 2020 - MAY 2021 (8 Months)

Tech Stack: Java, VueJS, Amazon AWS.

Role: Senior Engineering Manager at Cloudbeds. Working on the distribution vertical, leading the Distributed Systems team and the Channel manager team.

- Lead **two teams of 9 software engineers**, the distribution systems team in charge of **making systems scalable**, driving the engineering team into the microservices architecture; and the channel manager team distributing our inventory along +300 online booking channels.
- Responsibilities include technical product definition and mid-term/long-term vision, technological leadership, delivery, team growth, team health, and individuals progression.

SKILLS

Interpersonal Skills

Mentoring, Coaching, **Driving Technical Decisions**

Industry Knowledge

Scalability, Resilience, Observability, Software Architecture, Good Engineering Practices, API Design, Distributed Systems, Software Development Life Cycle (SDLC), Web Applications, Web Security, Agile Methodologies

Tools & Technologies

Languages and Frameworks: Go, Java, Groovy, Python, Kotlin, Ruby, Spring boot, Grails, Django, Ruby on Rails. **Cloud Platforms:** Amazon Web Services (AWS), Google Cloud Platform(GCP)

 Partner with the leadership to create the engineering department's career path and drive the engineering team's calibration.

Shipped:

- Drive the technology transformation into microservices.
- Along that time, the channel manager team attained a premier partnership with Booking.com.
- Partner with Google to be part of the Google Hotel Search pilot.



Cabify, Remote, Spain — Engineering Manager

APR 2019 - OCT 2020 (1 Year 6 Months)

Tech Stack: Golang, Redis, MySQL, NSQ, gRPC, Google Cloud Platform.

Role: Engineering manager at Cabify. Working on the Match team.

- Lead the creation of the Maps & Routes team.
- Lead a group of 7 software engineers collaborating with product and data science to improve our marketplace.
- Responsibilities include technical product definition and long-term/mid-term vision, technological leadership, team growth, team health, and individuals progression.

Shipped: We were in charge of the matcher, matching thousands of riders and drivers per matching round.

- Lead the creation of the Maps & Routes squad responsible for delivering the tools for providing routes and ETAs solutions for Cabify.
- That team reduced the operational cost of Cabify on other map services by more than a half in less than one year. By that time, the operating cost of mapping services was one of the company's highest expenses.
- Ship a tool to replace Google maps on calculations of ETAs based on a machine learning model that predicts ETAs. Later we extend that tool to replace Google Maps on routes calculation.



ebay eBay, Remote, Spain — Sr Engineering Manager

APR 2016 - APR 2019 (3 Years)

Tech Stack: Java, Spring Boot, Kotlin, Oracle, Kafka, Google Cloud Platform. Role: Tech Lead at Stubhub(an eBay company) worked on several teams across the company, like Delivery & Fulfillment, international, Buyer Experience, and Financial Services.

- Leading multiple teams of 10+ software engineers collaborating with product, design, and business to deliver delightful user experiences.
- Responsibilities for this role include product definition and vision, technical leadership, and team management.

Shipped:

- Lead the transformation of multiple services into Cloud Native Services.
- Drive the monolith extraction into microservices and bring them into the cloud.

Other achievements:

- Member of the SDLC Committee of the company.
- Organizer of the Engineering culture team inside Stubhub.

Technologies and tools: SQL (MySQL, PostgreSQL),

Redis, ElasticSearch, Git, SQL, Unix Systems.

CERTIFICATIONS

How to Manage a Remote Team

Coursera 2020

Getting Started with Go

Coursera 2019

Functions, Methods, and Interfaces in Go

Coursera 2019

Concurrency in Go

Coursera 2019

Ruby on Rails

Coursera 2016

Sun Certified Programmer for the Java Platform 5.0

Sun Microsystems 2009

Google Analytics Individual Qualification

Google 2011

LANGUAGES

English, Spanish

Ticketbis, Bilbao, Spain — VP of Engineering

NOV 2009 - APR 2016 (6 Years 6 Months)

Tech Stack: Java, Groovy, Grails, Spring Boot MySQL, Redis, RabbitMQ.

VP of Engineering - 2012 - 2016 (4 Years)
 Head Of Software Development - 2011 - 2012 (1 Year)
 Technical Lead / Principal Software Engineer - 2009 - 2011 (2 Years)

Role: Worked as a VP of Engineering at Ticketbis. I join to the company in their early days (employee #2).

- Lead the engineering group from its creation until we got acquired by eBay. By that time, the engineering group was more than 40 individuals in a technology group of over 80.
- Lead a group of four Tech Leads in the company.
- **Build the hiring process** from the beginning acting as Hiring manager for most of our incorporations.
- Drive the growth of the engineering department and its structure.
- Our main challenges involve scalability, reliability, and real-time processing.

Shipped:

- Build the platform of Ticketbis at the beginning.
- Lead the growth of the department.
- Provide the long-term roadmap for the department.

Universidad de Deusto, Bilbao — Associate Professor DEC 2012 - JAN 2013 (2 Months)

AOL, Dublin, Ireland — Senior Software Engineer
MAR 2008 - OCT 2009 (1 Year 6 Months)

In1Solutions, Dublin, Ireland — Software Engineer
OCT 2007 - MAR 2008 (6 Months)



Irontec, Bilbao, Spain — Software Engineer

SEP 2006 - SEP 2007 (1 Year)

EDUCATION

Universidad de Deusto, Bilbao, Spain — Computer Science
SEP 2002 - JUN 2007

SIDE PROJECTS



